Guide to the Naval History Society Collection 1721-1995 (bulk 1781-1936) MS 439
New-York Historical Society
- Series 10. Gustavus Conyngham (1777-1826)
  The collection includes Conyngham's diary from his incarceration by the British at Mill Prison; details of his claims against Congress for the payment of prizes for shipping captured by Surprize under his command; notes and manuscript drafts used in the publication of his papers by the Naval History Society in 1915 ("Letters and Papers relating to the Cruises of Gustavus Conyngham, a captain of the Continental Navy, 1777-1779," edited by Robert W. Neeser and printed by DeVinne Press, New York, as volume 6 of its publications); as well as original materials, some of which were used in the Society's volume. The latter are in the form of an unbound extra-illustrated volume amassed by John Sanford Barnes (see Series 3; see Series 11 for another extra-illustrated volume). Original documents mounted and described include Conyngham's 1777 commission in the Continental Navy, signed by John Hancock with interlinear notes by Benjamin Franklin, which had been thought lost and was rediscovered and purchased by Barnes in 1900; the brig Maria's commission signed by John Adams; an autograph letter signed by Alexander Hamilton; and numerous letters in Conyngham's hand.
  As commander of Surprize and Revenge, Gustavus Conyngham (1744-1819) was responsible for the capture of numerous British vessels, sale of whose cargo in friendly ports contributed to the financing of colonial forces. In 1779 he was captured by the British and incarcerated at Mill Prison, near Plymouth. Having had his commission confiscated, he later experienced difficulty in making claims to Congress for prize monies due to him. During the Quasi-War with France (1798-1800), he commanded Maria and later assisted in the defense of Philadelphia during the War of 1812.
  - Papers: original materials by and about Conyngham, amassed by John Sanford Barnes, 1777-1826 (Volume 1)
  - "Minutes from Gustavus Conyngham of his treatment [in Mill Prison], and remarks", 1779 April 27 (Volume 2)
  - "Observations on the report of Benjamin Mather Esq. to the late board of treasury, on the subject of Capt. Gustavus Conyngham's claim against the United States: as commander of the lugger Surprise and the cutter Revenge", 1787-1813 (Volume 3)
  - Notes: transcripts of letters and journal; notes on genealogy; newspaper clippings; correspondence, 1874, undated (Volume 4)
- Series 11. James Fenimore Cooper (1890)
  The series consists of James Fenimore Cooper's "The history of the Navy of the United States," originally published in two volumes in 1839, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes (see Series 3) into an eight-volume version with the addition of 427 portraits, 343 prints, 154 autograph letters signed, 32 maps, 23 broadsides, 10 signed documents, and 11 original water color sketches and portraits. It is accompanied by original and carbon typescripts of Barnes's lists of the extra illustrations, a manuscript notebook index of the additions, and a folder of photoreproductions.
  Among the autographed letters included are those of John Barry (see Series 5), Cooper himself, John Hancock, Commodore Bainbridge (Series 1), Isaac Hull (Series 27), David Porter, and Commodore Perry (Series 36), all of whom are represented elsewhere in the Naval History Society Collection. The illustrations document all the major naval battles, ships, and persons mentioned in Cooper's work.
  The practice of adding printed, manuscript, and visual materials as well as associated ephemera to previously published volumes probably began with James Granger's 1769 publication of "Biographical History of England," in which leaves were left blank specifically for the insertion of portraits by the purchaser. So-called extra-illustration reached its peak in the late 19th century as an organizational and collecting paradigm. An extra-illustrated volume very much reflects the collector and his or her interests, serving as a repository in the form of a cabinet of curiosities in which to display a wide range of associated, however remote, materials. Contemporary descriptions of extra-illustrated volumes often stress the volume of materials added as well as their quality, a significant expansion of the original being a virtue. Cooper's "History" provides a perfect setting for the physical manifestation of Barnes's lifelong interest in naval history and memorabilia, citing as it does every major naval engagement and personality. This work, when considered together with the Miscellaneous Manuscripts (Series 52), US Navy: Officer's autograph letters (Series 44), and John Paul Jones collections (Series 28), provides material evidence of Barnes's passion for collecting and its meticulous documentation.
  Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
  A bound version of the handwritten illustration list (originally from the Naval History Society Collection) titled "Catalogue of the extra illustrations, print, and manuscripts added by Captain James Sanford Barnes, U.S.N., to James Fenimore Cooper's History of the Navy of the United States, extending it to eight volumes" is available in the Reading Room. It lists the added materials, by page number, throughout the eight volumes and is indexed alphabetically by volume.
  - List of portraits from extra-illustrated "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper; original typescript and carbon, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Extra-illustrations from "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper; index book, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photostats from extra-illustrated "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, Undated (Box OS 1, Folder 5)
  - "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes, 1890 (Volume 1, part I)
  - "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes, 1890 (Volume 1, part II)
  - "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes, 1890 (Volume 1, part III)
  - "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes, 1890 (Volume 1, part IV)
  - "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes, 1890 (Volume 2, part I)
  - "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes, 1890 (Volume 2, part II)
  - "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes, 1890 (Volume 2, part III)
  - "History of the Navy of the United States" by James Fenimore Cooper, extra-illustrated by John Sanford Barnes, 1890 (Volume 2, part IV)
- Series 12. Francis Gregory Dallas (1837-1915; bulk, 1837-1859)
  The collection consists of incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence in English and German, two private journals, and photoreproductions of materials used by the Naval History Society in the publication of "The Papers of Francis Gregory Dallas, U.S. Navy. Correspondence and Journal, 1837-1859," edited by Gardner W. Allen, 1917, and published as the eighth volume of the Society's publications.
  Francis Gregory Dallas (1824-1890) served aboard Columbia in the Mediterranean and coastal Brazil, and aboard various ships in the Gulf of Mexico during the Mexican War (1846-1848). In 1848 he attended the Naval School at Annapolis, but was dismissed from the Navy in 1848 for having engaged in a duel. In 1849 he began three years of service in the Navy of the German Confederation, including as first officer of the imperial steam corvette Royal Ernst. He returned to the United States in 1852 and from 1854 to 1857 was aboard Decatur in the Pacific Squadron, along the west coast of the United States for the protection of white settlers and then in Panama. Aboard Dale, along the African coast, he seized barque Orion on suspicion of being engaged in the slave trade, returning with it to New York in 1859. He was subsequently mentally disabled and was retired from active duty.
  - Correspondence, 1837-1845 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1846-1847 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1849-1852 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photoreproductions for printed edition of Papers, 1877-1917 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, accounts, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Private journal, 1849 May 23 - 1857 July 7 (Volume 1)
  - Private journal "To Panama thence across the Isthmus to Aspinwall, New York et cetera Philadelphia Station & barque release to African Squadron and U.S. Ship Dale ", 1857-1858 (Volume 2)
- Series 13. USS Dictator (1865)
  The collection consists of a preprinted log book from and a black and white photograph of Dictator. Some of the book's pages are filled in by hand. Many are pasted over with undated newspaper clippings reporting news, general knowledge, games, quotations, and other information. The clippings on some pages have been partially torn off and writing is visible underneath. The photograph is inscribed in pencil: "US Monitor Dictator, 1865/ E.D. Robie, Chief Engineer US Navy and Inspector of Construction of Hull and Machinery of the Dictator."
  A single-turreted iron-clad monitor, Dictator was launched December 26, 1863, by Delamater Iron Works, New York, having been designed under contract with John Ericsson (see Series 16). It was commissioned November 11, 1864, under the command of J. Rodgers. As part of the North Atlantic Blockading Squadron, it cruised from December, 1864, until it was decommissioned at the League Island Navy Yard on September 5, 1865. It served in the North Atlantic Fleet in the 1870s and was sold in September of 1883.
  - Photo of US Steamer Dictator, 1865 (Box OS 1, Folder 6)
  - Steam log of U.S. Steamer Dictator for the quarter commencing April 1st 1865, 1865 April 1-July 1 (Volume 1)
- Series 14. William A. Duer (1862)
  The collection consists of a single volume documenting routine activities aboard US Flagship Wabash, on which Duer served as acting master's mate.
  Originally commissioned in 1856, by 1862 Wabash was a permanent part of the Charleston blockade, operating out of Port Royal. That year, a landing party from it occupied St. Augustine, Florida; another manned a battery that bombarded Fort Pulaski, Georgia, forcing its surrender. Its howitzers supported land troops at the Battle of Pocotaglio, South Carolina, on October 22, 1862. Wabash later joined the North Atlantic Blockading Squadron and saw duty in Spain and the Mediterranean after the Civil War before being decommissioned in 1912. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
  - US Flagship Wabash "Watch, Station, Fire and Quarter Bill kept by William A. Duer, Acting Master's Mate", 1862 (Volume 1)
- Series 15. William R. Durand (1861-1865)
  The collection includes journals and diaries, some of which incorporate both written entries and pasted in clippings from the US Navy Journal. The 1862-1863 volume includes printed accounts of the battle between the Confederate steamship Virginia (originally Merrimack) and USS Monitor in 1862. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
  Vessels in the North Atlantic Blockading Squadron were responsible for preventing Confederate ships from supplying ships in Virginia and North Carolina, and for supporting Union troops. Those in the South Atlantic Blockading Squadron operated between Cape Henry, North Carolina, and Key West, Florida.
  Mystic assisted in the capture or destruction of four blockade runners off North Carolina in June-September 1862. In May 1863, it supported the Army during an expedition up the York River.
  Mohawk joined the South Atlantic Blocking Squadron in June 1862, serving out of Port Royal from June, 1863, for the next year, until it underwent repairs in Philadelphia.
  Both Philadelphia and John Adams served as flagships of the Squadron, the latter of the inner blockade off Morris Island (Charleston, NC).
  Paul Jones had participated in attacks on Fort Wagner (Charleston, SC) in July 1863, returning to New York for repairs and rejoining the squadron in September. It continued coastal operations until August of that year and in 1865 joined the East Gulf Blockading Squadron.
  Commissioned in January, 1865, Muscoota was at Norfolk, Virginia, in May, 1865, when it was ordered to Key West as part of an effort to prevent Confederate President Jefferson Davis escaping abroad. It remained in the Gulf of Mexico area at least until August, 1866, was decommissioned in 1869, and then sold as a merchant steamship.
  - Navy Journal: North Atlantic Blockading Squadron, U S Steamer Mystic (4" rate), 1861 December 11 - 1862 February 20 (Volume 1)
  - Naval Diary: North Atlantic Blockading Squadron, U.S.S. Mystic [clippings 1862 October - 1863 August], 1862 February 21 -1863 August (Volume 2)
  - Navy Journal: South Atlantic Blockading Squadron, U.S. Steamer Mohawk (4" rate"), 1862 June 23 - 1863 Aug 16 (Volume 3)
  - Navy Journal: U S Steamer Mohawk (4" rate), South Atlantic Blockading Squadron, 1863 August 17 - 1864 January 2; Flag Steamer Philadelphia, 1864 January 5 - February 22; U.S. Ship John Adams, 1864 February - April 2, 1863 August 17 - 1864 April 2 (Volume 4)
  - Navy Journal: South Atlantic Blockading Squadron, U.S. Ship John Adams, 1864 April 3 - April 27; U.S. Steamer Paul Jones, 1864 April 27 - July 12, 1864 April 3 - 1864 July 12 (Volume 5)
  - Navy Journal North Atlantic Ocean and Gulf of Mexico. United States Steamer Muscoota, 1865 January 5 -August 25 (Volume 6)
- Series 16. John Ericsson (1831-1893; bulk 1862-1888)
  The collection includes original correspondence to and copies from John Ericsson (the latter predominantly in the hand of his secretary, Samuel W. Taylor, and a few autograph) as well as telegrams, invoices, receipts, writings, clippings, articles, an account book, and a volume listing his articles on torpedo warfare. The materials were a gift in 1912 to the Naval History Society from Ericsson's biographer William Conant Church, and the correspondence is annotated and underlined throughout in various colors, perhaps by him as part of his research for "The Life of John Ericsson" (New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1890). Undated materials appear to have been from Church's research and papers, and include separated and unidentified documents. The materials are mostly in English, with some in Swedish and German. Portions of this collection relating to the Civil War have been digitized and are available to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
  The collection documents many aspects of Ericsson's engineering interests and projects: the building and testing of ironclad warships to his specifications for the United States (USS Monitor, 1862) and other governments (Peru: May 1862; Greece: January 1869; Spain: May 1869; China: October 1880, spring 1883); the costs of construction through his extensive contact with Delamater and other ironworks and foundries as well as negotiations with Congress (1864-1865); applications and renewals of patents (1830s, 1840s, December 1864, July 1866); experiments with solar energy (1868, July 1872); design and testing of torpedo warships, including detailed expenses for Destroyer (January 1873, September 1874, April 1875, 1878-1882, January 1889) and reports on its trials (October 1883); as well as various complete lists of ironclads built to Ericsson's specifications (May 1866, December 1867, July 1877).
  Highlights of the collection include copies of Ericsson's January 20, 1862, letter to Assistant Secretary of the Navy Gustavus Vasa Fox (see Series 17), proposing the name Monitor for his ironclad vessel; and his January 30, 1873, letter to President Ulysses S. Grant explaining that the torpedo systems currently in use are inadequate for the country's defense.
  An extensive collection of Ericsson's papers is housed at the Library of Congress.
  Born in Sweden in 1803, Ericsson emigrated first to England (1826) and then to the United States (1839). Having shown early promise as an engineer, and holding numerous patents for steam-powered engines, he designed the first screw-driven steamship to cross the Atlantic (Robert F. Stockton, 1839) and the first propeller-driven steam warship for the US Navy (USS Princeton, 1842). In 1861 he contracted with the Navy to build in 100 days an ironclad warship, Monitor, which successfully fought the Confederate ironclad Virginia (originally Merrimack) at Hampton Roads on March 9, 1862, before sinking off Cape Hatteras later that year. After the Civil War, he pursued his interests in torpedo-armed vessels, and in a variety of scientific and engineering subjects, including solar energy. He died in New York in 1889 and was interred in Sweden in 1890.
  A chronological inventory of the papers of John Ericsson (from 1831 to July 1865 only) in the Naval History Society's collection was prepared in 1984 and is available in the repository.
  The John Ericsson papers owned by the American Swedish Historical Foundation are available on microfilm.
  The New-York Historical Society's Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection includes three autograph letters of John Ericsson's.
  - Correspondence, 1831-1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1857 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1858-1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1862 January 3 - February 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1862 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1862 April 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1862 April 15-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1862 May 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1862 May 15-31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1862 June - July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1862 August - September (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1862 October (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1862 November (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1862 December (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1863 January (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1863 February (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1863 March (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1863 April (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1863 May (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1863 June (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1863 July - August (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1863 September (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1863 October (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1863 November - December (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1864 January (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1864 February 1 - 18 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1864 February 19 - 29 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1864 March (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1864 April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864 May (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1864 June 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1864 June 16-30 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1864 July (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1864 August 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1864 August 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1864 September (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1864 October 1-18 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864 October 19-31 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1864 November (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1864 December (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1865 January (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1865 February (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1865 March (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1865 April (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1865 May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1865 June - July (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1865 August (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1865 September (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1865 October (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1865 November (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1865 December (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Undated [1831-1865] (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1866 January (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1866 February (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1866 March (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1866 April (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1866 May (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1866 June (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1866 July (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1866 August (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1866 September (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1866 October (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1866 November (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1866 December (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1867 January (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1867 February (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1867 March (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1867 April (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1867 May-June (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1867 July-August (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1867 September - November (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1867 December (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1868 January (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1868 February-March (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1868 April-May (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1868 June-July (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1868 August (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1868 September - October (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1868 November - December (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1869 January - February (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1869 March (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1869 April (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1869 May (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1869 June (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1869 July (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1869 August (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1869 September (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1869 October (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1869 November (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1869 December (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1870 January (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1870 February - March (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1870 April (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1870 May - June (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1870 July - September (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1870 October - December (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1871 January -February (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1871 March - April (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1871 May - July (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1871 August (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1871 September - October (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1871 November - December (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1872 January - February (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1872 March - April (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1872 May - June (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1872 July - September (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1872 October- December (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1873 January (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1873 February - March (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1873 April - May (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1873 June - July (Box 11, Folder 4)